Inventory of the Joel Martin Halpern papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Joel Martin Halpern papers
1922-2007
Halpern, Joel Martin.
76035
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
110 manuscript boxes, 4 cubic foot boxes (49.9 linear feet)
The collection contains grant proposals, conference papers, minutes, reports, studies, writings, notes, correspondence, electronic bulletins, and printed matter related to economic and social development of the Southeast Asia region, and American social science studies of the area; ethnology and social and economic conditions in Southeast Asia, Eastern Europe (especially Yugoslavia), and developing countries elsewhere; and the Yugoslav civil war.
Administrative Information
Access
Boxes 1-5 and 92-95 closed until 2023 December 20. The rest of the collection is open for research.
Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976, with additional increments between 1976 and 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Joel Martin Halpern Papers, University of Massachusetts Amherst
Joel Martin Halpern Collection, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Joel M. Halpern Papers, John F. Kennedy Library and Museum
Joel M. Halpern Papers, National Anthropological Archives, Smithsonian Institution
Joel Halpern Photograph Collection, Jones Library
Joel M. Halpern Balkan Archive, University of Bradford
Joel Halpern Collection, University of Graz
Joel M. Halpern Collection, University of Alberta Libraries
Joel M. Halpern Laotian Slide Collection, University of Wisconsin-Madison
Biographical Note
1929 April 8 Born, New York City, New York
1950 B.A., history, University of Michigan Studied Eskimo settlements on the Seward Peninsula of Alaska
1951-1952 Studied at the Russian Institute, Columbia University
1953-1954 Conducted research in former Yugoslavia
1955 Lecturer, Department of Anthropology, Columbia University
1956 Ph.D., anthropology, Columbia University Author, dissertation, Social and Cultural Change in a Serbian Village Research associate, Human Relations Area Files, American University, Washington, D. C.
1956-1958 Field Service Officer, Community Development Division, International Cooperation Administration, Luang Prabang, Laos, Foreign Service Reserve
1958 Author, A Serbian Village Author, Aspects of Village Life and Culture Change in Laos
1958-1963 Assistant professor of anthropology, University of California, Los Angeles
1959 With support of the Rand Corporation, conducted research in Laos, resulting in the study The Lao Elite: A Study of Tradition and Innovation
1959-1961 Consultant, Rand Corporation
1963-1967 Associate professor of anthropology, Brandeis University
1964 Director, Brandeis Summer Field Training Program, Bosnia, Yugoslavia
1965-1967 Fellow, Russian Research Center, Harvard
1966-1970 Member, Mekong Seminar of the Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG), Asia Society
1967 Author, The Changing Village Community
1967-1992 Professor of anthropology, University of Massachusetts at Amherst
1969-1970 Resident fellow, MIT-Harvard Joint Center for Urban Studies
1970-1971 Visiting professorship, Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat and Arnold Bergstrasser Institute, Freiburg, Germany
1972 Author, with Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, A Serbian Village in Historical Perspective
1974 Senior research fellow, Center for Urban and Community Studies, University of Toronto
1975 Served on a grant review panel for the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health
1975, 1978 Senior exchange scientist, National Academy of Sciences
1976 Author, The Changing Peasantry of Eastern Europe
1983- Joint appointment with Judaic Studies Program, University of Massachusetts
1989 Author, with Lucy Hong Nhiem Nguyen, The Far East Comes Near
1992- Professor emeritus
Scope and Content of Collection
The Joel Martin Halpern papers document Halpern's career as an anthropologist. The collection includes grant proposals, conference papers, minutes, reports, studies, writings, notes, correspondence, printouts of electronic bulletins, and printed matter related to economic and social development of the Southeast Asia region, and American social science studies of the area; ethnology and social and economic conditions in Southeast Asia, Eastern Europe (especially Yugoslavia), and developing countries elsewhere; and the Yugoslav civil war. Although the collection has not been arranged, the index to major groups can serve as a guide to the collection.
During his career as an anthropologist, Halpern traveled extensively for his scholarly work. He conducted fieldwork in a number of countries, including former Yugoslavia (in the areas of Serbia, Croatia, Slovenia, Macedonia, and Bosnia) and Laos. Halpern began his fieldwork endeavors as a student, spending his summers in northern Ontario, the Swedish Lapland, and Eskimo settlements in Alaska. His doctoral research took him to former Yugoslavia, where he and his wife, Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, spent a year in the Serbian village of Orašac. Yugoslavia would become a primary area of focus for Halpern, along with Laos. Later in his career, Halpern studied Jewish communities in Massachusetts. Halpern's curriculum vitae, which can be found in the Biographical file, details his fieldwork, as well as his professional positions and numerous writings.
Throughout his career, Halpern frequently traveled to former Yugoslavia for research and fieldwork opportunities. The Yugoslavia file contains Halpern's fieldwork notes, including kinship charts of Orašac residents, and Halpern's research and notes, including photocopies of archival documents from the 1600s to 1900s. Box 36, folder 7 contains information on various projects related to Yugoslavia.
In addition to his work in Yugoslavia, Halpern also conducted research in Laos. The Laos file contains fieldwork notes, conversation transcripts, and detailed letters written by Joel and Barbara Halpern describing Laos and their work.
Based on his fieldwork and research, Halpern produced a wealth of articles and books, many of which were coauthored by Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern. The Writings contain materials written and edited by Halpern, as well as pamphlets for other projects he was involved with, such as photograph exhibits. The collection includes many Laos Project papers based on research done in 1956 and 1957. Also included are writings published for the University of Massachusetts at Amherst International Area Studies Programs Occasional Paper Series.
In addition to his fieldwork, Halpern taught courses at University of Massachusetts at Amherst, University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), and Brandeis University. The collection includes Course material for classes Halpern taught on Eastern Europe, the USSR, and rural peasant societies.
While Halpern was a professor at UCLA in the 1960s, he was given funds to select and purchase materials on Yugoslavia for the library. In the early 1970s, Halpern worked on a project to create a handbook of research resources on Eastern, Central, and Southeastern Europe. Material documenting these projects can be found in the UCLA file.
Halpern was involved in the Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG) of the Asia Society as a member of the Mekong Seminar from 1966 to 1970. The mission of SEADAG included promoting scholarly collaboration between Asians and Americans, encouraging indigenous research capabilities in Southeast Asia, stimulating an interdisciplinary approach to development research and encouraging research on development problems, and supporting the research of graduate students. Material on SEADAG includes grant proposals and evaluations (including for a research program funded by the Agency for International Development), scholarly papers, executive committee correspondence, and seminar reports, which detail the general content and major conclusions of SEADAG meetings.
Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, the wife of Joel Halpern, was a medical anthropologist and professor at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. She often conducted research with Joel and coauthored papers with him. In 1990, Barbara gave an interview for Bulgarian TV to promote interest in creating a Bulgarian multiple sclerosis organization. For years after the interview, Barbara received letters from members of the Bulgarian public regarding multiple sclerosis. In addition to these letters, the Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern file contains a curriculum vitae and flyer for one of her projects. See also the writings series for articles cowritten with Joel Halpern.
The collection includes several typescripts of Serbian poet and essayist, Milovan Danojlić, which were given to Halpern by the author for safekeeping.
The Subject file mainly contains articles and speeches (including drafts and conference papers) by other academics on topics such as development and agricultural economics. There are also several files on United States culture.
The collection includes Printed matter, such as academic papers, development reports, newspapers, magazines, textbooks, and clippings related to countries where Halpern conducted research, especially countries of former Yugoslavia and Laos. The collection includes textbooks and other published educational aids from Serbia, Macedonia, Bosnia, Croatia, Bulgaria, Russia, and the United States. Conference papers and programs for various conferences on Eastern Europe and Russia can be found in the Conference file.
The Photographs series contains black and white slides of life in Eastern Europe and photocopies of photographs of Bosnia. The Audiovisual material series contains three VHS video tapes, including video produced for Serbian television.
Index of Major Groups
7, 13, 24, 31, 42, 43, 55 Biographical file, 1960-1990. Includes curriculum vitae of Halpern and documents related to accusations of Halpern's involvement with United States intelligence services.
21-22, 30-32, 36-37, 67 Yugoslavia file, 1948-1975. Includes fieldwork notes, research, photocopies of archival documents, and information on various projects involving Yugoslavia.
24, 27-30, 91 Laos file, 1956-1988. Includes articles, bibliographies, edited volumes, and exhibit catalogs on Yugoslavia, Laos, and other countries of research. Includes articles coauthored by Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern.
8-10, 14-15, 19-21, 23-27, 29-30, 34, 36-37, 41, 43, 48-49, 53, 55, 65, 67-68, 91, 98-99, 101, 104 Writings, 1950-1998. Includes articles, bibliographies, edited volumes, and exhibit catalogs on Yugoslavia, Laos, and other countries of research. Includes articles coauthored by Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern.
40, 47, 99 Course material, 1964, 1980-1990. Includes course descriptions, syllabi, and reading assignments.
32-33 UCLA file, 1962-1973. Includes correspondence and invoices related to projects to collect library materials and create a bibliography.
6, 10, 13-14, 44-48 Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG) file, 1961-1976. Includes grant proposals and evaluations, reports, correspondence, and meeting minutes. Includes material related to the Mekong Seminar.
10, 14-15, 37, 51, 91 Russian Research Center, Harvard University, 1951-1979. Includes seminar notes, papers, correspondence, and calendars.
42, 51, 70-78, 101, 104 Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern file, 1990-1995, undated. Contains correspondence from members of the Bulgarian public regarding multiple sclerosis and curriculum vitae. See also Writings for articles coauthored with Joel Halpern.
49 Milovan Danojlić file, 1974-1981. Includes typescripts of essays and poetry.
20-21, 31-32, 38, 52, 56-61, 66, 68, 96-97, 100-104, 106-108 Subject file, 1946-2004. Includes writings by others, printed matter, and correspondence.
6, 7-9, 12-13, 15-20, 27, 29-31, 33-35, 37-40, 42-44, 51-54, 56, 61-63, 65, 68-69, 79-89-91, 98-103, 105-106, 108-113 Printed matter, 1927-2007, undated. Includes academic papers, reports, textbooks, and clippings on Yugoslavia, Laos, and other countries.
6, 7, 11-13, 17, 30, 33-34, 40-41, 43-44, 59, 62-63, 67, 89-91, 101, 105, 108 Conference file, 1959-1999. Includes conference papers and programs.
14, 30, 32, 38, 96 Photographs, 1922-2007. Includes black and white slides of life in Eastern Europe and photocopies of images in Bosnia.
114 Audiovisual material, 1986-1993. Contains three VHS video tapes. Titles are inscribed from labels and may not match tape content.
Asia Society.; Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group.; Asia, Southeastern--Social conditions.; Developing countries.; Ethnology.; Europe, Eastern--Social conditions.; Social sciences--United States.; Yugoslav War, 1991-1995.; Yugoslavia--Social conditions.
- CLOSED (Box 1-5)
- Printed matter
  - Printed matter on Vietnam, 1959-1965 (Folder 6: 1-2)
- Conference file
  - Mediterranean Social Anthropological and Sociological Conference papers, 1970 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Soviet and Eastern European Agricultural Conference papers, 1965 (Folder 6: 4)
- Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG) seminar reports, 1973-1974 (Folder 6: 5)
- Biographical file
  - Curriculum vitae of Halpern, 1988 (Folder 7: 1)
- Conference file
  - Conference brochures, 1970, 1976 (Folder 7: 2)
- Printed matter
  - "North Vietnamese Interference in Laos,", 1964 (Folder 7: 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Increment of August 1989
  - Printed matter on Vietnam and other countries, 1963-1988 (Folder 7: 4-7)
  - Development reports and newspapers, 1967-1975 (Folder 8: 1-5)
    Includes reports on Vietnam, Laos, and Yugoslavia
- University of Wisconsin and University of Michigan informational materials, 1970-1971, undated (Folder 8: 6)
- Writings
  - University of Massachusetts at Amherst International Area Studies Programs Occasional Paper Series, printed copies, 1977-1979, 1983 (Folder 8: 7)
    Includes paper written by Joseph Obrebski and edited by Barbara and Joel Halpern
  - "Selected Papers on a Serbian Village: Social Structure as Reflected by History, Demography, and Oral Tradition," edited by Barbara and Joel Halpern, printed copy, 1977 (Folder 9: 1)
- Printed matter
  - Reports on Vietnam, 1961-1969 (Folder 9: 2-6)
- Russian Research Center, Harvard University, seminar notes and papers, 1965-1974 (Folder 10: 1-4)
- Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG), seminar meeting notes, 1968-1969 (Folder 10: 5)
- Writings and other projects, 1973-1982 (Folder 10: 6)
  Increment of April 1983
- Conference file
  - Academic papers, 1960-1970 (Folder 11: 1-6)
    Includes papers for the Mediterranean Social Anthropological and Sociological Conference, the Soviet and Eastern European Agricultural Conference, and the Far Western Slavic Conference
  - International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences papers, 1973 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Mediterranean Social Anthropological and Sociological Conference papers, 1970 (Folder 12: 2)
- Printed matter
  - Selected translations on Eastern Europe, 1961 (Folder 12: 3-4)
  - Yugoslavia and other countries, 1960-1983 (Folder 12: 5-7)
    Includes bibliography created by the American-Yugoslav Project in Regional and Urban Planning Studies
- Agency for International Development presentation to Congress on Vietnam, 1971 (Folder 13: 1)
- Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG)
  - Library documentation project, correspondence and proposals, 1968-1969 (Folder 13: 2)
  - Mekong Seminar meeting minutes and transcripts, 1969, undated (Folder 13: 3)
  - Mekong Seminar meeting minutes, 1969 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Seminars, 1966-1969 (Folder 13: 5)
- Mekong bulletins and secretariat notes, United Nations, 1971-1973 (Folder 13: 6)
- Progress report for Nepal, 1956-1958 (Folder 13: 7)
- Biographical file
  - Curriculum vitae and biographical information, 1981-1984 (Folder 13: 8)
- Conference file
  - Mediterranean Social Anthropological and Sociological Conference papers, 1970 (Folder 13: 9)
- Printed matter
  - Academic papers, 1960-1962 (Folder 13: 10)
- Photographs
  - Slides, circa 1920s-1950s (Folder 14: 1-8)
    Black and white slides of daily life, most likely in Eastern Europe. Includes images of people in traditional dress, buildings, and objects.
  - Photocopies of photographs and slides, 1922-1951 (Folder 14: 9)
    Black and white inscribed images of people in traditional dress and buildings. Duplicates some of the slides present in the collection.
- Letter to Margaret Mead and writings, 1971, undated (Folder 14: 10)
- Research proposals to National Science Foundation on Yugoslavia, 1960, 1965 (Folder 14: 11)
- Russian Research Center, Harvard University, event calendars, 1978-1979 (Folder 14: 12)
- Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG)
  - Seminar reports, 1969-1976 (Folder 14: 13)
  - Reports on research, 1970, undated (Folder 14: 14)
- Agency for International Development presentation to Congress on Vietnam, 1970 (Folder 14: 15)
- Printed matter
  - Academic papers, 1959-1974 (Folder 15: 1)
    Includes papers presented at conferences
- Writings
  - "Social and Cultural Change in a Serbian Village," dissertation, annotated typescript, undated (Folder 15: 2)
  - Macedonia sister-city research project, 1973, undated (Folder 15: 3)
    "Report on Yugoslavia" and correspondence with the Center for a Voluntary Society
  - "Communism and Anthropology: A Report on Field Work in Yugoslavia, Oct. 1961-Nov.1962,", 1961-1962 (Folder 15: 4)
    Includes letters to Albert C. Spaulding
- Peoples of the far north translations, 1953-1955 (Folder 15: 5)
- Russian Research Center, Harvard University
  - Correspondence and papers, 1964-1970 (Folder 15: 6)
  - Historiography, undated (Folder 15: 7)
  - Papers and seminar notes, 1960-1970 (Folder 15: 8)
- American Anthropological Association, Committee on Research Problems and Ethics, correspondence and writings, 1966 (Folder 15: 9)
- Printed matter
  - Yugoslav Facts and Views and Yugoslav News Bulletin, 1965-1980 (Folder 16: 1-5)
  - Yugoslav Facts and Views, 1960, 1977 (Folder 17: 1-2)
  - Translations by the U.S. Joint Publications Research Service concerning the USSR/Russia, 1961 (Folder 17: 3-5)
- Conference file
  - "Eastern Europe's Peasant Legacy and the Prospects for Private Agriculture," conference of the East European Program, schedule and papers, 1989 (Folder 17: 6)
- Printed matter
  - Translations by the U.S. Joint Publications Research Service, 1960-1961 (Folder 18: 1-6)
  - Development reports, 1970-1974 (Folder 19: 1)
    Includes reports of Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG)
  - Vietnam printed matter, 1965-1967 (Folder 19: 2)
- Statements from Department of Defense and military officials, 1973 (Folder 19: 3)
- Writings
  - Printed copies, 1964-1979 (Folder 19: 4-5)
    Includes writings co-authored with Barbara Halpern and edited by Joel Halpern
- Printed matter
  - Papers and newsletters on Soviet Russia and of the International Council of Jews from Czechoslovakia, 1971-1976 (Folder 20: 1)
    Increment of September 1989
  - Academic papers on Europe, including papers presented at conferences, 1967-1976 (Folder 20: 2)
- Writings
  - "Inuit Images and Culture" exhibition, 1962-1988 (Folder 20: 3)
    Increment of July 1988
  - Printed copies coauthored with Barbara Halpern, 1964, 1986-1987 (Folder 20: 4)
- Subject file
  - Marby, John, 1965-1966, 1971 (Folder 20: 5-6)
  - Field, Mark (Soviet Women), 1964 (Folder 21: 1)
  - Frey, Frederick W. (Turkey), 1966, undated (Folder 21: 2-3)
  - Inkeles, Alex, 1952-1966 (Folder 21: 4-5)
- Writings
  - People in States, 1972 (Folder 21: 6)
    Fourth grade textbook
- Yugoslavia file
  Copies of archival documents and notes on cities in Croatia and Serbia
  - Coding instructions for Yugoslav interviews, circa 1961-1962 (Folder 21: 7)
  - Bobovac census, 1948 (Folder 21: 8)
  - Slano
    - Council of Appeals (1704-1708), undated (Folder 22: 1)
    - Slano archives, Liber Vir Idis, undated (Folder 22: 2)
    - Lamenta Di Slano (1797-1804), undated (Folder 22: 3)
    - Court trials (1671-1674), undated (Folder 22: 4)
    - Letters and communications (1705-1799), undated (Folder 22: 5)
    - Diversa Slani translation, undated (Folder 22: 6)
  - Arandjelovac archives, undated (Folder 22: 7-10)
    General note
    Arandjelovac district contains the city of Orašac
  - Topola (1863), undated (Folder 22: 11)
  - Vribica, 1863 tax census notes, undated (Folder 22: 12-13)
  - "The Question of Serfdom at the Vienna Parliament, 1848,", undated (Folder 22: 14)
  - Croatia, Bobovac, copy of 1960 agricultural census (Folder 22: 15)
  - Arandjelovac, undated (Folder 22: 16-21)
- Writings
  - Aspects of Village Life and Culture Change in Laos, prepublication copy, 1958 (Folder 23: 1)
  - University of Massachusetts at Amherst International Area Studies Programs Occasional Paper Series, printed copies, 1979-1983 (Folder 23: 2)
  - Harvard Encyclopedia of American Ethnic Groups, annotated copy, circa 1980 (Folder 23: 3)
  - "Perspectives on Inuit Culture" catalog, edited by Halpern, 1988 (Folder 23: 4)
  - Conference papers, 1976-1981 (Folder 23: 5)
  - Mekong Basin Development Laos and Thailand, Selected Bibliographies, printed copy, 1974 (Folder 23: 6)
  - Bibliography of Miscellaneous Research Materials on Laos, printed copy, 1971 (Folder 23: 7)
  - "The Pulley, the Memoir of a Bronx Industry," writing by Carl Halpern, with an introduction by Joel Halpern, 1983 (Folder 23: 8)
  - "Selected Papers on a Serbian Village: Social Structure as Reflected by History, Demography, and Oral Tradition," edited by Barbara and Joel Halpern, 1977 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Annotated typescripts and printed copies, 1961-1989 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Laos Project papers, typescripts and printed copies, 1957-1961, undated (Folder 24: 3-4)
- Laos file
  - Draft report of development in Laos, 1985 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Reports on Laos and telephone book, 1974-1988 (Folder 24: 6)
- Biographical file
  - Curriculum vitae of Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern and Joel Halpern, 1984, 1988 (Folder 24: 7)
- Writings
  - Printed copies, 1963-1986 (Folder 25: 1-3)
    Includes writings by Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern
  - Typescripts, 1959-1974 (Folder 25: 4-5)
  - "A Bibliography of Miscellaneous Research Materials Pertaining to Laos, Thailand, Cambodia, Vietnam, and the Mekong River (Second Revised Version)," typescript, 1971 (Folder 25: 6)
  - Printed copies and typescripts, 1964-1990 (Folder 26: 1-2)
  - Laos Project papers, 1961 (Folder 26: 3-8)
  - Laos Project papers, 1961, undated (Folder 27: 1-7)
  - Macedonia Sister City Project and "A Third of a Century Studying a Serbian Village: Why?,", 1973, 1986 (Folder 27: 8)
- Laos file
  - Letters written by Joel and Barbara Halpern, 1957 (Folder 27: 9)
  - Phoenix interview, 1973 (Folder 27: 10)
  - Memorandum on Mekong field trip, 1957 (Folder 27: 11)
  - Transcript of conversations between A. M. Halpern and Joel Halpern, 1959 (Folder 27: 12)
    Conversations related to the Laotian elite
  - "Festival in the Royal City" by Pinhkham Uparavarn, 1958 (Folder 27: 13)